Welcome to this what's new in web
services in Business Central 2024
release wave one.
My name is Kenny Pontoppidan.
And I'm Jens Møller Pedersen.
And together we work on the Business
Central server
where we will talk about
web service stack.
Let's get started.
In this wave, we added support for
cookies in HTTP client. I'm already
getting hungry.
Yes.
Uh so, there's a new data type and full
support of of cookies including caching
so to make it faster.
That basically allows you as developer
to to use cookies in third-party
applications in your HTTP requests uh on
block in one of the scenarios that you
asked for in the server.
So, we have a new cookie data type, new
AL methods to handle cookies, and also a
way to reuse cookies in in later
responses with what we call I think
cookie caching.
Yes.
So, HTTP client has
a new method called use response
cookies. And if you set that to true,
the server will attach automatically
cookies in subsequent responses.
We have a new cookie data type where you
can set
set cookies and and use them, expiry
date, and so on.
And
and then there are new methods on
on other data types related to HTTP
client. So, you can get cookie names
from the response message data type.
You can get a cookie
once you know its name from also from
the HTTP response message data type.
And
similarly, not on the response message,
but on the request request message data
type, similar
methods get cookie names and get cookie.
So, you can use
these methods there.
As well as on the request message, you
can set the cookie either by name or
value.
Or if you already have a cookie object,
you can also set it there.
You can remove cookies. And basically
that that allows you to work with
cookies.
Yeah, and if you use the use request
cookies, then basically what you receive
last will then get added to the request
that you send next. What you receive in
a response gets sent with the next one.
Yeah.
And that actually happens as the last
thing.
All right, we also want to have a little
teaser. We didn't make it for this
release, but we expect to ship it in a
minor release, which is direct support
for patch. In the HTTP client data type.
And this was actually part of this
huge work we did on HTTP client
documentation. So, we lifted the
documentation for HTTP client related
things to outgoing web service calls.
Including also documented how how you
can use patch with with other methods.
But that might not be needed soon
because there will be native support.
But if you work with calling external
services from HTTP client, including
maybe writing wrappers for Azure modules
or other APIs, then then go check out
the new documentation. There's a lot of
new things there also related to
robustness on on your code. So, make
sure that you know what's available once
you start
going down this path.
All Now we've talked about you calling
out from Business Central using HTTP
client, but let's also talk about the
changes that are happening if you're
calling into it through OData. We've
added support for the in operator, which
is much shorter notation rather than
having the equals this or equals that,
etc. So now you can just use customer
number in and then have a list of
values.
We've also improved the performance of
OData by reducing the number of calls,
basically changing a bit the logic from
what happens normally within AL because
you seldomly
stop a find call when using OData.
Normally you want everything. So now
we're using find first for one row, find
for two to 50 rows, and then find set if
you are requesting more than 50 rows
either through the top operator or
implicitly through the max page size.
So Jens, I've noticed a pattern here. We
I mean, we do these every 6 months,
these sessions. And we always talk about
improving the OData stack, improving API
rest stack, but we never talk about
soap.
No, that's because that's not where we
invest. We're investing in OData.
Soap
is used in a number of legacy
integration scenarios. Um but
it is clear that it is the OData API
that that we are investing in.
So that also means, hint hint,
that you should move your integrations
away from soap into a more modern world.
Yes.
Now another place where you see where we
favor OData over soap is how we deal
with the number of incoming web service
requests.
We have changed that significantly in
this release. In previous versions,
basically, you had
five requests per tenant, and then if
you had more than five concurrent
requests, they would be queued up.
Now, you have
a queue per user.
So,
if a user has three requests, they will
be executed immediately. They will not
be queued up because each user has their
own
queue, which gives higher throughput for
environments. At least it allows us to
start a lot more sessions, and you don't
risk that one user is starving all your
other users on this tenant, so that they
cannot do their web service requests.
Ed,
I have the best I I story like for that.
Yeah.
So, imagine you're you have that person
in finance updating Power BI reports,
and suddenly down on the warehouse,
people can't scan, use the scanners.
Yes.
That's kind of what we're solving with
this.
So, so Lone from finance will now be
able to update her Power BI reports,
and John and the others in the warehouse
will be able to to still click through,
and and pack things, and have them
shipped.
Yeah, and it also means now that
if you have more users, you effectively
also have more parallel web service
requests, which you didn't have to the
same degree before.
So, we are tracking them per user at any
given period in near real time.
Um now, there is still a service
protection limit. It is possible to just
flood the system, in which case we're
still limiting it to protect it. That's
the queuing mechanism that you have per
user, etc. So, you can still get
uh too many request responses, the HTTP
429. Uh Uh that is still possible.
But, let's take a look at how
if we look at it graphically, then
before, basically,
the number of users, if you went to an
environment, you would have three users
in the first one, they were limited to
five, and you had the same limit
regardless of the number of users.
Whereas now, you basically have a number
of parallel streams allowing you into
each environment, but there is still a
global limit. Now, we have never seen
that global limit be reached in
production, because we have rolled this
out now. It is now active in the
majority, I think. Oh, I don't know the
exact percentage, but we're rolling it
out right now. So, it is in effect in
most parts of the world.
And if you happen to reach the global
limit, then we're doing a round robin of
users, meaning that it'll be a new user
who gets the next spot when the global
limit is reached. But, in general, you
shouldn't see this happening. We'll be
scaling out if the system is under
pressure, etc. But, even in that case,
you'll still see throughput.
So, speaking of scaling, yes, we also
did some secret work on the server that
we're not talking too much about. But,
maybe a little bit, you can tell us a
little bit about it?
Yeah, because you might wonder what has
happened. Why can we suddenly open up
for a lot more requests? And we have
optimized the way we have handle
sessions, so that we use a lot less
resources just to keep a session alive,
which is pretty large refactoring of the
um
of the server. But, it allows us to do
things like this.
Cool.
So, if you meet us at us at conferences,
um
buy us a cup of tea, and maybe we can
talk more about certain internals.
Yeah, because it's not really something
that you can see. It's not a new AL
method, etc. It's just how we deal with
all of the requests and sessions
internally.
All right.
So, part of this release was also a lot
of work done on documentation for
incoming outgoing web services.
You saw the the work done on HP client,
but similarly
a lot of new content on how to
troubleshoot web service errors and how
to troubleshoot web service performance
is now available in in the
documentation. The easiest is probably
just to use the search mechanism in docs
to find these articles. I'm I'm pretty
sure you will find them
find them useful.
Finally, we have some breaking changes
that are happening in this in this wave
and some that are coming in upcoming
releases in version 26 and later.
So, the first is that delta links with
APIs is now removed. That was
announced a couple of years back,
which means if you set the OData track a
changes in the HP header, it has no
effect. So, the code dealing with this
has been removed.
Similarly, API schema version now
defaults to 2.0 also in this wave. You
can still revert to older versions of
the API schema. We just need to set that
in in the HTTP header.
And then upcoming changes, this is just
a warning that in a later version,
version 26 or later, API version 1 will
be removed.
Yeah, so you can set it to explicitly
use V1 for now, but it'll only save you
a year or so. Yeah.
We also have an upcoming change on SOAP
web services, specifically web service
SOAP web services on
pages in the Microsoft owned by
Microsoft publisher
that will be removed in a later release
so that you cannot in the web services
page
open up a soap web service on on
Microsoft pages.
All right, and with that there are some
there is a call to action. First of all,
if you're building integrations with
other products, go take a look at the
documentation. If you're starting
something new, there is a lot of new
material in there that's going to help
you. And if you're in doubt about how
something works, go check even if you've
checked before
because
a lot has been added there.
And of course, if you need cookies
Who doesn't?
Yeah.
Then it is now supported in AL.
That's it. Before you leave a few
relevant launch event sessions that you
might want to look into look into.
Since this is web services as as Jens
Jens Jens mentions, there's a lot of new
documentation on integrations. So a new
session on that.
Also,
in case you are in
AL developer, there's a similar session
for key updates in in learning content
for you.
And if you're into this server database
thingy that we have going
And who's not?
Who's not? I mean, we are.
The first two sessions here, what's new
in AL runtime and database, second one
or what's new in reporting with Excel
layouts is in in kind of that. And if
you are developer, there's no way around
it. Of course, you want to watch what's
new in Visual Studio Code and AL
development.
Finally
AKA links, in case you don't know them.
So the first one, BC Yammer, is where we
discuss things that are not maybe
something we want to take to the public
social media.
Um,
all is the the one aka link to rule them
all. BC ideas is where we discuss future
feature requests for for future
versions of Business Central. Social
media on X and LinkedIn, we are there.
And last, BC office hours is where you
can either
go and
get to in in live office hours or watch
recordings of existing ones.
And with that,
Jens and I says, thank you.